<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Case of the sheriffs for the year 1682, or, The third years paper in regard to the act for corporations being the case also of the dissenting ministers in regard to the act of Oxford : in a second and third sheet, together with the first revised, strengthened and reprinted ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18154</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12601362</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12601362</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64177</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31183)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64177)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 347:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Case of the sheriffs for the year 1682, or, The third years paper in regard to the act for corporations being the case also of the dissenting ministers in regard to the act of Oxford : in a second and third sheet, together with the first revised, strengthened and reprinted ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Title page is cropped in filmed copy. Beginning-p. 10 photographed from Union Theological Seminary Library, New York copy and inserted at the end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64177:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CASE Of The Sheriffs, For the YEAR 1682. OR, THE Third Years Paper In Regard to the Act for Corporations. Being the CASE alſo of the <hi>Diſſenting Miniſters,</hi> In Regard to the Act of <hi>Oxford.</hi> In a Second and Third Sheet, together with the Firſt Reviſed, Strengththened, and Reprinted. Upon more than ordinary preſſing Cauſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting both the Preſervation of ſuch Minſters, and their People, and the Univerſal Safety of the Nation.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Thou ſeeſt Brother, how many Thouſands of</hi> Jews <hi>there are which believe, and they are all Zealous of the Law. And they are informed of thee, that thou teacheſt all the</hi> Jews <hi>which are among the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>to forſake</hi> Moſes. <hi>Do therefore this that we ſay unto thee, that all may know that thoſe things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they are inform'd concerning thee, are nothing; but that thou thy ſelf alſo walkeſt Orderly, and keepeſt the Law.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurst,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chappel,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:64177:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64177:2"/>
            <head>To thoſe Two Worthy Citizens, Who Shall be CHOSEN <hi>Sheriffs of London,</hi> For the YEAR 1682.</head>
            <p>WHether a Cup of Wine drunk by the <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> or the Votes of a Common-Hall, according to the Charter, ſhall have the Preheminence to make a <hi>Sheriff</hi> of this City, it is but a few Weeks or Days (it is like) will bring into Tryal. This Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per does ſuppoſe ſuch an Election: and it is the great difficulty onely, as to the holding Sheriffs in point of Conſcience when Elected, that is here concerned. We Dedicate theſe Sheets therefore beforehand, to thoſe who ſhall be ſollicited to be <hi>Candidates,</hi> for their Premeditation, and after to the <hi>Choſen.</hi> The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from the beginning, for Printing this <hi>Caſe,</hi> are as follows.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> To take the Oath, and Subſcribe the <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the literal ſtrict Conſtruction, appears, in our
<pb facs="tcp:64177:3"/>judgment, unlawful; and conſequently, unleſs by ſome means or other the ſenſe be made publick in which a man does take them, (and that ſenſe alſo be juſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) he muſt forbear.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The <hi>Declaration</hi> is againſt the Conſciences of the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> in general, inſomuch as ſome Men who took the <hi>Oath,</hi> cannot ſubſcribe the <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration;</hi> and for any Conſciencious Men therefore to do it now, and not declare their Reaſons of Satisfasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were to Sin againſt <hi>the Brethren</hi> if they own them, or to diſclaim them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> By doing this, a Man ſhall give occaſion to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to follow his Example, and if he preſent them not in his Grounds or Reaſons, thoſe that follow ſhall do it without the ſame Reaſons, <hi>and through his knowledge ſhall</hi> ſuch <hi>periſh. But when ye ſin ſo againſt the Brethren, and wound their weak Conſciences, ye ſin againſt Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> The Epiſcopal Party are generally apt to think the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> to be Hypocrites and Knaves, and ſay, <hi>Theſe Men</hi> refuſe theſe Injunctions out of <hi>humour,</hi> or for their <hi>profit,</hi> but they will ſwallow them as well as <hi>we</hi> for <hi>Honour,</hi> or for <hi>Advantage.</hi> If any conſiderate Men therefore ſhall <hi>Swear</hi> and <hi>Declare,</hi> and not give us ſome rational Account of what they do, (or ſome others for them) they must not only wrong themſelves, but the whole Generation of ſuch Men, and cauſe <hi>the Name of God</hi> (in regard to them) <hi>to be Blaſphemed.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64177:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Firſt Sheet,</hi> Being The SHERIFFS CASE.</head>
            <head type="sub">Whether, and How they may Lawfully Qualifie themſelves for their Holding the Office, according to the Act for <hi>Corporations.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN this Act there are Two things impoſed, An <hi>Oath,</hi> and A <hi>Renunciation</hi> of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> And we muſt lay down this<note n="*" place="bottom">To this Rule, there is a double Extreme: The <hi>One</hi> is of thoſe who think, a Man muſt take every In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>tion in the ſtrict litteral Conſtruction, and can ſubmit to it no otherwiſe. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is of ſuch who ſuppoſe, that if a Man can frame any Interpretation of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is but reaſonable, he may take the Words in that Senſe, and be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe is ſo rigid, that there is nothing can be impoſed, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> at it; and the <hi>laſt</hi> ſo looſe, that nothing can be impoſed, but we ſhall ſwallow it. The true <hi>Medium</hi> is this, we muſt ſit down, and conſider what we believe to be the Meaning of the Lawgiver; and if we can ſubmit to an Impoſition, in that Senſe or Meaning which we believe <hi>theirs,</hi> we muſt do it; but if we believe their Senſe to be ſuch, as we cannot take it in <hi>that Senſe,</hi> we muſt forbear it, and ſuffer. Pray ſee more about this Rule, in a Book entituled, <hi>A Peaceable Reſolution of Conſcience, touching our Preſent Impoſitions,</hi> Pag. 121. to 126.</note> 
               <hi>Rule</hi> at firſT, That all Impoſitions of our Superiours, muſt be taken in the Senſe and Meaning of thoſe that Impoſe them: There need be no Scruple elſe in Submiſſion to any thing enjoyned. The bottom is this; The <hi>Law</hi> is the <hi>Will</hi> of the <hi>Lawgiver;</hi> and it is the <hi>Lawgiver</hi>'s <hi>Meaning,</hi> which is his <hi>Will,</hi> howſoever the Words of the <hi>Law</hi> is expreſſed.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64177:4"/>
            <p>Not that when we <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> the <hi>Words</hi> and the <hi>Meaning,</hi> we do <hi>divide</hi> them. An <hi>Impoſition</hi> muſt be taken in the <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Words,</hi> and the <hi>Senſe</hi> of the <hi>Words,</hi> but the <hi>Senſe</hi> of the <hi>Words</hi> muſt be the <hi>Meaning</hi> of the <hi>Lawgiver:</hi> Although there are <hi>Words</hi> ſometimes alſo to be <hi>underſtood,</hi> when it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent either from the Subject-matter, or from other <hi>Acts</hi> where that Meaning is fully, or fuller declared. The <hi>law</hi> it ſelf now (we know) hath no <hi>Meaning</hi> or <hi>Intention,</hi> but the <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> or They that make it. The <hi>Parliament</hi> here is the <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> and this <hi>Oath</hi> then muſt be <hi>taken,</hi> and <hi>Renun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation made</hi> in the Senſe and Meaning of the Major Part of the <hi>Parliament</hi> which paſſed the <hi>Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we muſt alſo premiſe thus much, That it is not for any <hi>Sheriff, Alderman,</hi> or any other Perſon upon whom this <hi>Oath</hi> is impoſed, (for we muſt begin with <hi>That</hi>) to put a <hi>Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of his <hi>Own</hi> upon it, which is to be taken only in <hi>Theirs</hi> that paſſed the <hi>Act;</hi> but to conſider verily, what he believes to be <hi>that Meaning,</hi> which is indeed the <hi>Lawgivers.</hi> Not to determine neither and ſay, <hi>This is the Meaning;</hi> but to be able to ſay, I <note n="*" place="bottom">There is a Court then is ſet up for every one in his own Breaſt, Let him go to his Conſcience, and ask, What thinks he really, as in the Preſence of <hi>God,</hi> if he could ask the <hi>Impoſers</hi> of theſe things; whether it is their Will, that he ſhould be of another mind, in theſe Particulars that croſs his Aſſent, or leave his Station? If his Conſcience tells him, it is verily perſwaded, that it was their Intention in the Injunction, he is to Honour <hi>God</hi> in his patient Suffering their Pleaſure. But if he is perſwaded in his Soul, that this is utterly againſt their ſills (and was), and that the things be ſcruples at, or as be ſcruples them, never came into their Minds unleſs to admit them, onely they paſsed them in the groſs, never intending that they ſhould put a Barr in Conſcience to any, and if he could ask them, he believes they would certainly allow him in them. Here he is (I ſuppoſe) to put ſuch a Senſe or Meaning then upon the Injunction, as may be favourable to his Scruples, and yield it his Submiſſion. <hi>Ex Libro Praedict. p. 125.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Believe</hi> this to be their <hi>meaning,</hi> which is neceſſary to every one that takes it, to determine for himſelf, that he may act in Faith in what he does.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:64177:4"/>
            <p>We muſt add, That when we ſay the <hi>Parliament</hi> is the <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> we underſtand by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> and conſequently, that the Senſe of the <hi>Law,</hi> (and ſo of this <hi>Oath</hi>) muſt be always that Senſe, wherein the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> did concur with the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> with <hi>Both.</hi> If there be any Senſe therefore of an Impoſition, which may be ſuppoſed to be the Meaning of the <hi>King,</hi> and not of the <hi>Houſes;</hi> or of <hi>One</hi> of the <hi>Houſes,</hi> and not the <hi>Other;</hi> or a <hi>leſſer</hi> part of <hi>either Houſes,</hi> and not the <hi>majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>both;</hi> that Senſe muſt be ſtill lookt on as too narrow, and ought not to ſcruple the Conſcience: the true Senſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging the <hi>Subject,</hi> being the <hi>concurrent</hi> Senſe of the <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> who as aſſembled joyntly to this end of Legiſlation, not <hi>One</hi> without the <hi>Other,</hi> but all <hi>Three</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as <hi>One Corporation</hi> (and not otherwiſe) are the <hi>Lawgiver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is this ſenſe to be collected, from the firſt floating Apprehenſions of any one, that moves a matter in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> but from the digeſted Thoughts of <hi>both Houſes,</hi> after a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Debate, and the thing hath thrice paſſed in them <hi>both;</hi> ſo that no Senſe of any Impoſition, but that which is agreable to Reaſon, and more eſpecially to the Fundamental Laws of the Conſtitution, muſt be received as the<note n="*" place="bottom">When the Scripture is ſaid not to be of private Interpretation, the Meaning is, that we muſt not put any Senſe of Man, upon it, let it be never ſo reaſonable; but we muſt ſtill take the Senſe of the Holy-Ghoſt, that inſpired it; and if you ask, What is, or How ſhall we know what is the meaning of that Divine Author? The way is to compare one Text with another, and all with the Analogy of Faith, and Oeconomy of the Goſpel. We muſt ſay the ſame of Laws. The <hi>Law</hi> is not of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Interpretation,</hi> but the <hi>Meaning</hi> of the Lawgiver: and if you ask, how we ſhall know their meaning, we ſay likewiſe by this (as one way), the comparing one <hi>Act</hi> with other <hi>Acts,</hi> and all of them, by their Univerſal Conſent with the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Conſtitution. See <hi>Ibid.</hi> 125.</note> Meaning of a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> the Reaſon being, becauſe the nature of the <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> is ſuch, as it cannot be infringed by an Act or Law for the <hi>Adminiſtration.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:64177:5"/>
            <p>This is a Note to be laid in here, that by and by will be needful: And thus much therefore farther, and no leſs being premiſed, we proceed.</p>
            <p>By <hi>taking Arms,</hi> Let us ſuppoſe the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> believe the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> meant the raiſing an Army, or War; and by the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>King's</hi> own Sacred <hi>Perſon,</hi> as there is nothing elſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed can be meant: And we can ſee no<note n="*" place="bottom">The only Objections here which are of weight, may be reduced to two Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. One is the Caſe of <hi>Private</hi> violence, as ſuppoſe a Prince ſhould go to Raviſh a Virgin, and ſhe catches up the next Weapon or Inſtrument to defend her ſelf. In this Caſe, or the like, we anſwer, this Defence is not to be accounted <hi>taking Arms</hi> in the ſenſe of this Act. The other is a Caſe of <hi>Publick</hi> violence; as ſuppoſe a Prince ſhould go about to alienate his Kingdom, or ruine his Country, or the like. We anwer, we are not for all that to return violence upon his Perſon; and as for his Officers, Followers, or Armies, the Solution muſt be attended in the next Clauſe of the Oath.</note> Objection, which may not be anſwer'd from this Little, in the Firſt Clauſe of the Oath. <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ſwear, That I hold</hi> (Theſe words, <hi>I hold, I believe,</hi> or the like, muſt doubtleſly be underſtood) <hi>it is unlawful to Take up Arms againſt the King,</hi> (His Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Rightful Government) <hi>upon any Pretence whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>David's</hi> Heart ſmote him for cutting off but <hi>Saul's Skirt,</hi> when he was actually in Arms to <hi>defend</hi> hemſelf againſt <hi>Saul's Forces,</hi> only becauſe he was the <hi>Lord's Anointed:</hi> It is not in this firſt Clauſe (any one may conjecture) but in the enſuing, where the chief Scruples againſt the <hi>Oath</hi> are to be removed.</p>
            <p>In the Second Clauſe, By <hi>thoſe Commiſſionated by Him,</hi> let us ſuppoſe they beleive the <hi>Parliament</hi> meant, &amp; could mean, no other than ſuch as have a due Authority from HIm, and exerciſe it only according to Law: And ſo long as the <hi>King's Authority,</hi> and <hi>ſuch Commiſſions</hi> are one, (or the ſame,) we can ſee no more difficulty remaining in the Second Clauſe, than in the former: <hi>And I do abhor</hi> (that is, <hi>diſown</hi> or <hi>diſclaim</hi>) <hi>that Trayterous Poſition, of taking Arms by his Authority againſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64177:5"/>His Perſon, or againſt any Commiſſionated by Him, in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of ſuch Commiſſions:</hi> That is, <hi>Legally</hi> Commiſſionated by Him, in the <hi>Legal</hi> purſuit of ſuch Commiſſions.</p>
            <p>It is not to be imagined, that the <hi>Parliament,</hi> when they paſſed this <hi>Act,</hi> (that is, the <hi>Major</hi> part of them) ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign the ſetting up an Arbitrary Government in the Nation: But if the meaning of <hi>thoſe Commiſſionated by Him,</hi> be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than thus, they muſt deſign it. An <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> as ſoon as they paſſed this Clauſe in any Act, muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted to <hi>Commence,</hi> or be declared to be alwayes the Right of the <hi>King.</hi> A thing moſt abſurd to be believed, and in the contrary Belief whereof, the moſt ſcrupulous Man (we thank <hi>God</hi>) may reſolvedly take this Oath.</p>
            <p>In the Third Clauſe, we diſtinguiſh an <hi>Endeavour</hi> to <hi>change</hi> or reform any thing in Church or State, which we think conducive to the good of the Nation in a <hi>Parliamentary</hi> way only, as is allowed by the Fundamental Law and Courſe of the Realm, from an <hi>Endeavour</hi> in any other way that is not warranted by the ſame: to wit, in a ſeditious way, or in ſuch manner <hi>as they did in the late Times,</hi> when they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the Extirpation of Frelacy by force <hi>againſt,</hi> and <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> the <hi>King's</hi> Conſent in <hi>Parliament,</hi> (which may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be the aſſured Senſe of the Majority in the <hi>Houſes,</hi> when they paſſed this <hi>Act</hi>) and ſo long <hi>as to do ſo</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">It may be ſaid, the <hi>Parliament</hi> raiſed Armes, before they declared Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to <hi>Extirpate Prelacy,</hi> and condemn the whole <hi>Parliament</hi> War, when they would have us declare it unlawful <hi>to do that Now,</hi> which they did <hi>Then</hi> (or, as <hi>of late hath been Practiſed,</hi> to uſe the Words of the Militia Acts): But let this be granted, it follows, then muſt their Meaning here indeed be, that we are not to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour any Alteration of Government in <hi>the Way they did then</hi> (which, being out of doubt of, the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> can Swear); but nothing more, we are ſure, is condemned in <hi>This Clauſe</hi> of the <hi>Oath,</hi> whatſoever elſe be intended in the <hi>former</hi> Clauſes of it, and the <hi>Militia Acts,</hi> in regard to the <hi>Beginning</hi> of the War, as well as the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs</hi> of it: And as for that point, Whether in the peculiar Caſe of thoſe times, there was any thing might be lawful, or any way juſtifiable to be done <hi>Then</hi> (when the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſes</hi> (the One Corporation) were divided, and he had paſſed an <hi>Act</hi> not to Diſſolve them without their Conſent, which is a Caſe never like to happen any more, and ſo no danger to put it) which <hi>Now</hi> is certainly unlawful, is a Queſtion we have nothing to do with, and interpoſe nothing to offend any.</note> 
               <hi>now,</hi> may be acknowledged (as aſſuredly) to be unlawful, and what ought to be diſclaimed, the offence muſt be over in the laſt part of the <hi>Oath</hi> alſo: <hi>And that I will not endeavour any Alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of Goverment either in Church or State;</hi> to wit, in any manner not warranted by the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> or any otherwiſe, than by Act of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:64177:6"/>The Preamble of the <hi>Oxford Act,</hi> (where the ſame Oath is Impoſed on the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> Miniſters) declaring it to be made, for the preventing the Opportunity of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling into Folks the Principles of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> may give ſome Credit to this Expoſition: But it is this one clear Reaſon or Argument we reſt pon, for our Confirmation in it. The great Thing intended by this Oath, is the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Government, in the Fundamental Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, againſt all Alteration. But the Conſtitution of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being ſuch in the <hi>Foundation,</hi> that whatever is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or convenient to be altered, it may be propoſed to that end in Parliament: to take away that Liberty which is univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly radicated in the whole Nation in order thereunto, were a piece of the greateſt Alteration that could be, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently never to be underſtood, as intended by the <hi>Lawgiver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi> (the Renunciation whereof, is the Second thing here impoſed) it is an <hi>Oath</hi> ſo long ſince in Being, <hi>that,</hi> 'tis two to one but Both the Sheriffs that ſhall be Choſen, (as well as thoſe of late before them) never took; ſo that they may ſafely ſay, there lies no Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation upon them at all from it; And as for others that did, we humbly conceive, that being taken in it's <hi>Complex Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration,</hi> as it was preſſed and uſed at that time, for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of the People to the Extirpation of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and Change of Church-Government without the King, againſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64177:6"/>His Conſent and Publick Declarations, and by Force; it muſt needs be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful,</hi> and could not bind any body <hi>to do ſo:</hi> and conſequently we truſt, that ſuch Gentlemen ſhall not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God, or any good Men, if they farther ſubſcribe this Declaration, which is alſo required: <hi>I. A. B. do declare, Taht I hold there lies no Obligation on me, or on any other Perſon, from the Oath commonly called,</hi> The Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>to endeavour any Change or Alteration of Government either in Church or State; And that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawful Oath, and impoſed on the Subjects of this Realm, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the known Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We confeſs here, that theſe Words, <hi>[to endeavour any Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Government in Church or State]</hi> were put in by the Author, unwittingly thinking them to be in this <hi>Act,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are in others, and it paſſed two Impreſſions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Knowledge of ours, that it was otherwiſe: But now do we let them ſtand, <hi>de Induſtria,</hi> becauſe it appears, they are to be<note n="*" place="bottom">The Meaning of a Law (or of the Law-giver) may be gathered from the Pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſome <hi>Acts;</hi> the common underſtanding of the many; the ſpecial Judgment of the Wiſe; the Diſcourſing with ſome of thoſe that made the Law; which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it cannot be with all, or the greateſt part, that which ſeems moſt ſatisfactory is, when the ſame Perſons (or <hi>Parliament</hi>) do ſignifie their Mind by their own Words in ſome other <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Acts:</hi> And this being the Caſe here, we ſee not but ſome men may be as verily perſwaded, that theſe Words are to be ſupplied, or that this was the <hi>Parliaments Meaning,</hi> as if the Generality could be asked, and they had told them, This it was. However, let the <hi>Medium</hi> be what it will, whereby a Man comes to the Reſolution of his Belief about the Impoſers Meaning in this or any the like Impoſition, when he is once brought to a ſettled Perſwaſion and Conviction, that This or That, and no Other was their Meaning, if he can ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Wrods in the full Latitude of that Meaning, as he is fully perſwaded in his Conſcience, is all they intended in ſuch or ſuch an Injunction; then is he <hi>free</hi> to his own Determination. See <hi>Peac. Reſ.</hi> before quoted. p. 114.</note> underſtood, both from <hi>other Acts,</hi> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity Act,</hi> The <hi>Veſtry Act,</hi> The <hi>Oxford Act,</hi> which have the ſame Declaration with theſe words in it (wherein we are yet more confirm'd by that Act, where it is made a <hi>Premunire</hi> to ſay, There lies an Obligation upon any from this Oath, the <hi>Obligation</hi> being expreſſed, <hi>to do thus</hi>): As alſo, from <hi>the Nature of the Thing;</hi> for ſo long as the Meaning of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver is the Rule we go by, let us but ſuppoſe we could go to the ſame <hi>Parliament,</hi> Man by Man, &amp; ask them, Was it your Meaning by this Declaration, that any man, who took that <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> ſhould profeſs, that he is not bound to reform his Life, to repent to his Sins, to eſchew <hi>Profaneneſs, Popery,</hi> &amp; <hi>Schiſm,</hi> or the like things they then covenanted to do, becauſe that Oath in ſome reſpect otherwiſe was unlawful; the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, without Queſtion, would Anſwer NO, by no means; but our meaning was onely, that there lies no Obligation on any from that Covenant, to endeavour to <hi>Extirpate Prelacy,</hi> as it was there, or <hi>any Alteration of Government,</hi> as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64177:7"/>by us in other Acts. This being ſuppoſed then the undoubted Meaning, we go on.</p>
            <p>By ſome of the laſt words of the Declaration it appears, that this <hi>Oath</hi> was framed for the <hi>Subjects of the Realm,</hi> (we ſay, that this <hi>Oath</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi>) was, in the meaning of the Impoſers of this Declaration, <hi>the Subjects Oath,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the words, <hi>or any other Perſon,</hi> they muſt mean, <hi>or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subject:</hi>) which appears alſo manifeſtly in the <hi>preamble</hi> of it; <hi>We Noblemen, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpell, and Commons of all ſorts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the King.</hi> There is one part of it moreover expreſs for the <hi>preſervation of the King;</hi> we do ſuppoſe therefore, that though an <hi>Oath</hi> to the ſame main effect, or one like it, was impoſed on <hi>this King</hi> by the <hi>Scots,</hi> that <hi>Oath</hi> muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>another</hi> than this, and not the very <hi>ſame,</hi> being not ſo in every point, but an <hi>Oath</hi> indeed (as they call'd it) <hi>to confirm the Covenant,</hi> when He offer'd this very Exception againſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf, becauſe it was an <hi>Oath</hi> for the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> only.<note place="bottom">And that <hi>that</hi> Oath the <hi>King</hi> took, was indeed Another, or One purpoſely <hi>framed</hi> for Him, any that will, may ſee in the <hi>Form of his Coronation,</hi> in <hi>Dowglas</hi> Sermon. I CHARLES, <hi>King, do aſsure and declare by my solemn Oath, my Allowance of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League, and engage my ſelf to Proſecute the ends thereof,</hi> with other words ſet down there, p. 19.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64177:7"/>
            <p>And this being enough to ſave the Conſcience in <hi>one chief</hi> Scruple, (and chiefeſt one,) we will gather up again what is ſaid before into one Argument (which we fix upon) for a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſatisfaction in regard to <hi>all others.</hi> To own the <hi>KIng</hi> and his Authority in the ſame <hi>Oath,</hi> and yet to ſwear to change the Government <hi>without His</hi> Will, and <hi>againſt</hi> it, is (we think) <hi>in it ſelf unlawful.</hi> Such an <hi>Oath</hi> was the Covenant; and <hi>Qua</hi> unlawful, it muſt be unobligatory.</p>
            <p>And what indeed ſhall now hinder theſe Sheriffs to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, That there lies no obligation upon them, or others, from the Covenant, <hi>to endeavour any Alteration of Government;</hi> in that ſenſe as they ſwear before, that they <hi>will not endeavour any,</hi> in the third clauſe of the Oath preceding? For ſo long as the meaning of the Lawgiver, is no other than <hi>That</hi> which is made to appear there, upon the account given, and the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour</hi> which is here, and which is there, is the ſame out of doubt, we do not ſee but the Reaſon which does ſatisfie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Man upon the Point about taking the <hi>Oath,</hi> muſt be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for the <hi>Declaration</hi> alſo. In ſhort, <hi>There lyes no obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon any from this Oath, to do as they ſware <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t; It is in it ſelf unlawfull to do ſo; and the Impoſition of it was</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">It muſt be confeſſed, that the voluntary Omiſſion of theſe words that are to be underſtood in this <hi>Declaration,</hi> and the deſigned Oppoſition to the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding of the <hi>Parliament</hi> in thoſe times, without diſtinguiſhing Right from Wrong, in the <hi>Oath,</hi> and the high Strain of the <hi>Militia Acts,</hi> which ſeems to diſpoſſeſs the Subject of all Defence, againſt any Commiſſion of the <hi>King,</hi> be it what it pleaſe, are enough to make any ſearching Man indeed believe, that the Meaning of the <hi>Contrivers, Hatchers,</hi> and <hi>Compilers</hi> of ſuch Impoſitions, who for promoting their own Intereſt could find in their hearts to be Villains to the Common-wealth, and the Souls of Men, was more than thus: But we Anſwer, By diſtinguiſhing onely, <hi>Theſe</hi> are not the <hi>Lawgiver.</hi> The <hi>Lawgiver</hi> is the Generality of <hi>Beth Houſes</hi> with the King, who are never to be ſuppoſed Underminers of our Rights, or to have any evil Meaning, but to convene for Conſultation about the Common Good; and whatſoever Laws do paſs, they are to be believed to carry in them the Reaſon of Publick Benefit, or elſe they are no Laws. <hi>Quod non habet rationem publici commodi non poteſt pracipi, lege humana,</hi> ſay the Schools; and it is a Rule laid down to ſatisfy all by the Lord <hi>Coke. Quando Lex generaliter lequitur reſtringenda ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men eſt ut ceſſante ratione &amp; ipſa ceſſet; Cum enim ratio ſit anima vigor<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ipſius legis, non videtur Legiſlator id ſenſiſſe quod ratione careat, etiamſi generalitas prima facie aliter poſſit ſnadere.</hi> Inftitut. Par. 4. C. 74.</note> 
               <hi>illegal.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:64177:8"/>
            <p>In the Sacred Story concerning <hi>Rahab</hi> and the <hi>Spies,</hi> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that no body can be engaged any farther by an <hi>Oath,</hi> then what he agrees or conſents to in the taking it. Where he declares before-hand he will not be bound, he is free. We cannot tell how much <hi>larger,</hi> or how much <hi>narrower a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs</hi> others may draw to themſelves from that <hi>Inſtance,</hi> than we: But we will come to this Concluſion. We have laid down the <hi>Rule</hi> we are to walk by in theſe <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> and applied it to this <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Subſcription.</hi> If any Man is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in his Conſcience, that the Meaning of the <hi>Lawgiver</hi> was no more than thus, he may ſubmit to them Both, and make no ſtand: But if he believes their Meaning was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (or doubts that it was more than thus,) he cannot <hi>Swear</hi> or <hi>Subſcribe,</hi> but with <hi>Limitations;</hi> and he muſt declare thoſe <hi>Limitations,</hi> or <hi>Forbear.</hi> But if he ſhall <hi>Swear</hi> or <hi>Subſcribe</hi> (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing him <hi>one</hi> that <hi>doubts</hi>) w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>making a Declaration</hi> for <hi>himſelf</hi> (if this Paper will not ſerve for <hi>All</hi>) when he Takes the Oath, and Subſcribes the <hi>Renunciation</hi> enjoyn'd, that he does it <hi>in this Meaning, which we have all along expreſsed, ſuppoſing it true, and with theſe Explanatory Limitations to the meaning, if in any thing indeed it be otherwiſe,</hi> and ſo give (or throw) in this Paper to the Perſons before whom he is to do it; we are perſaded, that his <hi>Conſcience</hi> may receive Satisfaction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in his complyance with the<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>In Mr.</hi> Baxter's <hi>Funeral Sermon upon that holy Citizen Mr.</hi> Aſhhurſt, <hi>we take notice of this paſſage.</hi> Some may think that he wanted a Publick Spirit, beeauſe he avoided being a Magiſtrate, and payed his Fine rather than take an Aldermans Place; but it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to keep the Peace of his Comſcience—Yet I never heard him ſpeak uncharitably of thoſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Men who do what he refuſed, ſuppoſing that they, in words or writing, declared as open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they ſware and took the Declaration, that they took it but in ſuch or ſuch a lawful ſenſe; though he could not do ſo himſelf.</note> 
               <hi>Law</hi> in theſe Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>Whether they receive the Paper, and admit of your ſenſe or not, it is no matter; for they have no Power about it, and the thing will be alike known. And thus have we lent our <hi>hands</hi> to get the Concern'd over theſe blocks, and yet ſo, as to deliver alſo our <hi>Souls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:64177:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Second Sheet,</hi> Being The MINISTERS CASE, WITH THE SHERIFFS, In Regard to the <hi>Five Mile Act</hi> of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BY the Act at <hi>oxford</hi> there is this Oath enjoyned every <hi>Nonconformiſt Miniſter,</hi> upon the Penalty of debarring him the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within Five Mile of any Corporation. J. A. B. <hi>Do Swear, that it is unlawful to take Armes againſt the King, upon any pretence whatſoever: And that I abhor that Trayterous Poſition, of Taking Armes by the King's Authority againſt his Perſon, or any Commiſſionated by him: And that I will not at
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64177:10"/>any time Endeavour any Alteration of Government, either in Church or State.</hi> In which Oath there are three Clauſes.</p>
            <p>The Firſt and Second Clauſe of it, comes to this, That <hi>it is not Lawful to take Armes againſt the King, or any Commiſſionated by Him, upon any Pretence; No, not upon the Pretence of His Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Law. It is a Trayterous Poſition, to hold e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that lawful.</hi> And all this is true, plain, and to be granted, as ſoon as we do but under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand onely what <hi>to be Commiſſionated</hi> is. To be <hi>Commiſſionated</hi> by the King, is to have his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or Authority from him, to do ſuch a thing. If we take Armes againſt one that does do any thing by the <hi>Kings</hi> Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we take Armes againſt His Authority, and that is all one with taking Armes againſt the <hi>King;</hi> and conſequently, to <hi>declare</hi> it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to take Armes againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and againſt thoſe <hi>Commiſſionated by him,</hi> is in effect alſo but the ſame. The <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> and His <hi>Perſon,</hi> are both alike <hi>Sacred,</hi> and both theſe muſt be held alike <hi>inviolable</hi> on all hands. The queſtion then only will be this, What is the <hi>King's</hi> Authority? Authority <hi>(Poteſtas)</hi> is <hi>jus imperandi,</hi> a Right or Power to command: This Right or Power is given the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64177:10"/>
               <hi>King</hi> by Law. It is <hi>the Law makes the King,</hi> (ſays <hi>Bracton</hi>), <hi>Lex facit Regem;</hi> the meaning whereof is, that the Authority which the <hi>King</hi> hath, can be no other but what the Law does grant him. The Government (we know) with us is <hi>Regal,</hi> and not <hi>Deſpotical,</hi> and the <hi>King's</hi> Power, a Power onely <hi>to Govern by the Laws.</hi> If the <hi>King</hi> then ſhall Commiſſionate any to do that which is againſt Law, that Commiſſion is void; it is a <hi>Writing,</hi> but no <hi>Commiſſion;</hi> that is, it is <hi>without Authority;</hi> For the <hi>King</hi> hath none to give <hi>against</hi> the Law, but <hi>For</hi> the Law, who is the <hi>Executioner</hi> of it. For a Man then to act in ſuch a Matter wherein the <hi>King</hi> hath none to give, it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vain to plead a Commiſſion. If he be taken, and puniſhed, he muſt thank himſelf: this is no reſiſting the <hi>King,</hi> or any <hi>Commiſſionated</hi> by Him. For inſtance, a Prince gives Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Levy Money, without a Tax by <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> His Officers or Souldiers come here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and takes a Mans Goods; the Man runs for the Conſtable, and the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Charges the Neighbourhood in the <hi>King's</hi> Name to aſſiſt him, and ſo apprehends them, and brings them to the Juſtice; the Juſtice ſend them to Goal; and then the <hi>Judg</hi> Hangs them: And all this is juſtifiable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64177:11"/>ſuch Authority is none; and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore no <hi>Commiſſionated Officers,</hi> are but <hi>Thevies</hi> and <hi>Robbers;</hi> who, when the <hi>King can do no wrong,</hi> yet they <hi>do,</hi> and are juſtly Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for it. We ſee then here plainly, how we may declare it unlawful to take Armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>King,</hi> and againſt thoſe that are <hi>Commiſſionated by Him,</hi> upon one and the ſame Reaſon: For when no Man may take Armes againſt the <hi>King,</hi> or his Rightful <hi>Authority,</hi> and no body is indeed <hi>Commiſſionated by Him,</hi> but he that acts according to the Law, and ſo hath his Authority; it is, and muſt be unlawful to take Armes againſt thoſe that are <hi>Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onated by him,</hi> as well as againſt <hi>Himſelf.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that, if any act againſt the Law, and plead his Commiſſion, they be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by the Law,</hi> becauſe ſuch are <hi>not</hi> indeed <hi>Commiſſionated</hi> by him.</p>
            <p>For the third Clauſe of the Oath, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government is ſuch, as every Freeman hath a fundamental Liberty by the ſame, to endeavour the Redreſs of any Grievance, which he feels in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> comprizes under it the whole <hi>Government of the Church,</hi> as Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and may make any Alteration thereof, when <hi>Monarchy</hi> it ſelf belongs to the <hi>Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64177:11"/>This Part then of the People, which they have in <hi>our Government,</hi> reaches thus far. The Body do chooſe their <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> for <hi>Parliament;</hi> they may inform them of theſe Grievances; we may Petition them for Alteration; we may out of doubt, pray to God for their suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. Our <hi>Repreſentatives,</hi> then are to prefer the Bills, and get them paſſed, if they can do it. Thus much (let us ſay) is the <hi>Right</hi> of the People, no leſs than the <hi>bearing the Sword,</hi> (that is, the Execution of the Government) is the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> or a Negative Voice is the <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>Both Houſes.</hi> It is not now ever to be imagined therefore, that it was the Meaning of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> to diveſt any <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> of this Right, to which he was Born, becauſe he is a <hi>Nonconformiſt;</hi> neither can they indeed do it. It is not to be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that an <hi>Endeavour</hi> for the Government to act, or to exerciſe its proper acts, or to put its proper Power into Act, which is but to keep it alive, or keep it in motion, ſhould be <hi>that Endeavour,</hi> which the Majority of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> would have abjured in this Oath. It is not to be imagin'd, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> when they go about to preſerve the Government from any <hi>Alteration,</hi> ſhould have any ſuch Meaning, as muſt deſtroy its very <hi>Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64177:12"/>We determine conſequently, it muſt not be an <hi>Endeavour</hi> of any Alteration (ſuppoſed needful) in this way, that is, in a <hi>Parliamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> way onely, which they intended we ſhould renounce; but all <hi>Endeavour</hi> of altering Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in any other way or manner, than what is warranted by the Fundamental Law of this Kingdom. And if this Radical Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be left us, we ſee how we <hi>may,</hi> and <hi>muſt</hi> do as much towards Reformation of the Church, after ſuch an Oath is taken, as we may, or can do before we have taken it. We cannot endeavour any thing in a Seditious way, but we ſin againſt <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> which we dare not do; and the way which is lawful to be taken, is open to us ſtill. It follows, ſo long as we go by the Meaning of the Lawgiver, which is the Rule laid down to go by, we may both take the Oath, and it will do us no hurt to take it.</p>
            <p>For Surpluſage, it was propoſed in the <hi>Lords Houſe</hi> upon occaſion of the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon generally, that the Meaning of the Commiſſionated was <hi>Legally Commiſſionated,</hi> though they thought it not beſt to put it into a Bill for ſome prevailing Reaſons. The like was in the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> alſo, as it is ſaid. Now though a <hi>Vote</hi> of either <hi>Houſe</hi> be not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64177:12"/>to repeal a Law, it is enough to tell us the Meaning of the Lawgiver, which does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve this Caſe of Conſcience: Unto which, when we can add this alſo, that it is known to ſome, that the <hi>King</hi> hath ſaid it Solemnly more than once, in publick, and in private both, that he was not for an Arbitrary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but ſuch an one onely, as the Law gives him, (we mean in words to that purpoſe) what is there any Man can deſire more for his full Satisfaction in this Matter? What hinders, but this <hi>Oath</hi> may be taken? <hi>And when they had read the Epiſtle, they Rejoyced for the Conſolation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:64177:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Third Sheet,</hi> With Reſpect to the More Scrupulous, WHETHER Sheriffs, Miniſters, or Others, That are Concern'd, For this Fuller Confirmation about the <hi>Oath.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE are not unſenſible of what moment an <hi>Oath</hi> is, and the <hi>Declaration</hi> enjoyned, who have ſet our ſelves, as in the preſence of <hi>God,</hi> that muſt give an account before his Tribunal for every Word that we write, in our Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo ſolemn a Determination as this is. We warn every Man therefore, to be true to our Rule, and to take heed that he acts nothing, till he is firſt perſwaded in his own mind of what he does; For while we endeavour to give a Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Conſcience, of others, we muſt have a care of our own Souls.</p>
            <p>There are two main <hi>Objections</hi> in the Caſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is this. The <hi>Oath,</hi> and <hi>Renunciation</hi> of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which are here impoſed, ſeem to be framed in direct Oppoſition to the late <hi>Parliament</hi>-Cauſe. The <hi>Parliament</hi>-Cauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64177:13"/>ſtood upon this Foundation, That the Law is above the Will or Commiſſions. Upon the <hi>King's</hi> Reſtauration to his Throne, a New <hi>Parliament</hi> is called, and they by this <hi>Oath,</hi> and the like Impoſitions, are ſuppoſed to decide the controverſy. When we are put therefore here to renounce the Poſition of taking Armes by the Law, or the <hi>Kings</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, againſt any Commiſſionated by him, we muſt (upon this ſuppoſition) conceive the <hi>Parliament</hi> meant, that Poſition ſhould be abjured, whether thoſe Commiſſions be Legal or Illegal; for otherwiſe the Controverſy is not deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The Poſition of taking Armes by the Authority of the Law, againſt any Commiſſionated by the <hi>King,</hi> was not maintained on the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſide, but onely in Caſe thoſe Commiſſions were againſt Law; and unleſs we renounce the Poſition of taking Armes by the Law, againſt all Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though illegal, we renounce ot the Poſition of that <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this <hi>Objection,</hi> we Reply in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place; If the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament muſt be conceived to put thus much upon us, then muſt we believe that they took this for granted, that no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the <hi>King,</hi> indeed may be reſiſted, whether ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law, or againſt the Law; and if ſo, that the <hi>King's</hi> Commiſſions conſequently muſt be above Law, and his Power Abſolute. But to believe, that any <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould intend to allow the <hi>King</hi> ſuch a Power, is quite be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond ſober Reaſon. Let him believe this who can, upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Deliberation.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Second</hi> place, we ſay therefore, There is here two or three Suppoſitions, that are not to be yielded. It is but a falſe Suppoſition, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> intended a Deciſion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64177:14"/>of the Controverſie between the <hi>Kings</hi> ſide, and <hi>Parliament</hi> ſide, by this Oath. It were a very inadaequate Intention. It is a falſe Suppoſition, That this was any of the Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie between the Judicious (or thoſe that underſtood them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) of both ſides, who did certainly agree in this, That the Authority of the <hi>King</hi> is Royal, not Arbitrary; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that his Commmiſſions are valid, when according to Law, and not elſe. It is a falſe Suppoſition again, That thoſe few Men that contrived theſe Impoſitions, or compiled theſe <hi>Acts,</hi> were the <hi>Parliament.</hi> 'Tis true, that what is here urged may be ſufficient to ſuggeſt to a Man a belief, That the <hi>Intention</hi> of thoſe that were the Contrivers of theſe <hi>Acts</hi> (this <hi>Oath,</hi> and the <hi>Militia</hi> Preambles) might be no leſs, than to make the <hi>Kings Will equal to Law;</hi> at leaſt in the Matter of the Militia: but we ſay, and have ſaid in the <hi>Margine</hi> of one of theſe Sheets before, That theſe <hi>Contrivers</hi> or <hi>Compilers</hi> (a few miſchievous Men perhaps) were not the <hi>Lawgiver.</hi> The <hi>Lawgiver</hi> we have premiſed, and ſet out in the firſt Sheet, in the beginning, with advantage againſt this Suppoſition. We are by no means, to think that the Majority of the <hi>Two Houſes,</hi> as they agree to an <hi>Act,</hi> could conſent in this to make the <hi>King's</hi> Commiſſions above, or equal to Law, which were to change the Government which is <hi>Regal,</hi> into <hi>Deſpotical.</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> is the <hi>Will of</hi> the <hi>King, in conjunction with his Parliament;</hi> His Commiſſions are His <hi>Single</hi> Will only, and therefore leſs than the Law is.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Third</hi> place, we anſwer hereupon, That if an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion from this <hi>Argument</hi> ſhould ſink into the Mind of any <hi>particular Perſon</hi> ſo far as to perſwade him to think it <hi>probable,</hi> that this was the meaning of the <hi>Parliament;</hi> yet if a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Apprehenſion ſinck deeper, or another Argument be more prevailing, he muſt follow the more Praedominant <hi>Conviction.</hi> But there is no <hi>Argument</hi> ſo <hi>probable,</hi> but, that an <hi>Engliſh Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> ſhould intend to make the <hi>King</hi> Arbitrary, is more <hi>improbable.</hi> That they never meant this, will have the deeper impreſſion.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:64177:14"/>
            <p>In the <hi>Fourth</hi> place, We may therefore believe rather, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> thought not of theſe Poſitions, on both ſides, and the determination of them, (which indeed is not to be imagin'd of the Majority, whatſoever the Contrivers, or a few, might do) but in general, they thought of ſuch a Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which in the ill Conſtruction they would have abjured; or they intended to decry the Poſition upon which War was raiſed, but in ſuch a confuſed Underſtanding of it, as that they would have it renounced indefinitely, without intending the Renunciation of that implicite Truth in it, which they on all ſides hold to be the very Fundamental Right of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> People, according to the Conſtitution of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Fifth</hi> place, we will enlarge a little this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The <hi>Parliament</hi>-ſide ('tis true) held it lawful by vertue of the Law, (that is, by the <hi>Kings Authority</hi>) to reſiſt ſuch as are in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion by the <hi>King;</hi> but the Wiſe of them could diſtinguiſh the Caſe, when thoſe Commiſſionated did act according to Law, and when they did things contrary to Law; and though they held it lawful in <hi>One</hi> Caſe, they did not hold it ſo in the <hi>Other.</hi> The <hi>King's</hi> ſide, on the contrary, held it unlawful to reſiſt the <hi>Kings Commiſſions</hi> by his <hi>Authority,</hi> or by <hi>Law;</hi> but the <hi>Wiſe</hi> of theſe knew how to diſtinguiſh likewiſe theſe two caſes; and it is not to be belevied, but ſuch as Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> (who declares the Laws to be above the <hi>Kings</hi> Commiſſions) knew and held, that in caſe any ſhould come by the <hi>Kings</hi> Commiſſions to take our money by force, without an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> or the like, they might legally be reſiſted. Now, when ſuch a Poſition of the Unlawfulneſs to take Arms by the <hi>King's</hi> Authority, againſt ſuch as are Commiſſionated by Him, is required to be renounced, it is neceſſary to diſtinguiſh accordingly, in regard to the meaning of the <hi>Parliament:</hi> For though ſome might be willing to have it renounced univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, they that underſtood themſelves could not be of that mind: And if we could go to them all, and ask them one by one, Whether they underſtood the <hi>Oath</hi> ſo as that they would
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64177:15"/>have it held unlawful to reſiſt the <hi>King's</hi> Officers, or Forces, that came particularly to raiſe Money, without any <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>-Tax; who can beleive, the Majority would ſay, it was their meaning? I do not think one Man of the whole Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would have the face to ſay it, whatſoever privately he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. When the Poſition then is indefinite, but in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter neceſſary to be diſtinguiſhed, and the Queſtion is, What was the Meaning of the Majority? it can come only to this, That they would have the Poſition renounced in One Senſe, and that Senſe muſt be ſuch certainly, as the Government of the Nation, which is <hi>Regal,</hi> may be ſtill maintained, and not turned to <hi>Tyranny;</hi> for the Generality, beyond doubt, never once intended to do that by any of theſe Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Laſt</hi> place, We will add this, to ſtrengthen us in the reſt. That it is unlawful to take Arms againſt any <hi>Commiſſionated by the King,</hi> according to Law, is a Senſe wherein the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Two Houſes</hi> muſt agree, out of doubt: But that it is unlawful to take Arms againſt any <hi>Commiſſionated by Him,</hi> if they ſhall come with a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to do that which is contrary to Law, it was not the Senſe of <hi>Both Houſes,</hi> we may be ſure, becauſe the <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> (as we have ſaid in the <hi>Second Sheet</hi>) declared, That by the <hi>Commiſſionated,</hi> they all meant <hi>Legally Commiſſionated:</hi> And alſo, which is more, when it ſeemed not fit (for Reaſons otherwiſe, which they had) to have that word <hi>[Legally]</hi> put into the <hi>Oath,</hi> (though they agreed in their Judgment, <hi>Nemine Contradicente,</hi> that it was meant) they threw the <hi>Teſt</hi> out of the <hi>Houſe.</hi> Had the Major Part been of the mind, that the <hi>Comiſſions</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> may never be reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Why ſhould this Clauſe be explained? Had not the Major Part been of another mind, Why did not the <hi>Teſt</hi> paſs? Now, if a Man be but aſſured, that any one of the <hi>Houſes,</hi> or the <hi>King</hi> alone, be againſt ſuch or ſuch a Senſe, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to conclude for the Negative, <hi>This was not the Senſe:</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:64177:15"/>When a Man muſt find out ſuch a Senſe as that, wherein we can believe they all Three did agree, to conclude for the Affirmative, that <hi>This was it.</hi> The Reaſon of this was premiſed at the Beginning of the <hi>Firſt Sheet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much for the Firſt Objection, the Second fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows. By <hi>Government of the Church,</hi> we underſtand not <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy</hi> only in the Subſtance, which the <hi>Scripture</hi> approves; but our <hi>Dioceſan Epiſcopacy,</hi> as now Eſtabliſhed: Neither do we diſtinguiſh between Alteration <hi>in the Government,</hi> and <hi>of the Government,</hi> to come off ſo, which were Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Play. No, if any ſhall go about to take away the <hi>Biſhops Courts,</hi> or <hi>Officers,</hi> as their <hi>Lay-Chancellors, Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> the <hi>Arch-Deacons Courts,</hi> their <hi>Canons</hi> by which they act, or any of their <hi>Eſtabliſhed Authority;</hi> This we account an Endeavour to alter the Government. Now, when theſe are things we would have altered, how can we ſwear we will not Endeavour any Alteration of Government in the Church? How can this Oath be taken?</p>
            <p>For Anſwer to this, we have in the beginning laid down our Rule, and we muſt have our Recourſe to it, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly we muſt conſider what indeed we verily believe in our Hearts, the Lawgiver intended. Was it their Meaning then, by ſuch Impoſitions to fix the Church ſo, as nothing of this kind ſhould ever be altered, though by <hi>Parliament,</hi> and though there ſhould be never ſo much Reaſon for a Redreſs? We cannot think ſo far; and if they intended not this, then cannot All <hi>Endeavour</hi> be underſtood here, (<hi>viz.</hi> that which is ſuch only) but an Endeavour otherways. Their Meaning muſt be to debar us all Endeavour of altering even ſuch things as theſe in any way, but this only, (the way of <hi>Parliament</hi>) which is warrantable by the Conſtitution of the Kingdom. This we have ſaid, and muſt ſay it over. A <hi>Parliament</hi> is never to be believed to conſent to that which is not in their Power. The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government is ſuch in its Conſtitution, as that Part thereof, ſo far as this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64177:16"/>comes to, (an Endeavour to alter ſuch things as theſe, when they are Grievances) does ſtill lie in the Body of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and the Meaning of a <hi>Parliament</hi> muſt never beconſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo, as to deſtroy that Liberty, which is Fundamental to the Kingdom. That which belongs to <hi>Every Body</hi> by vertue of the <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> (we muſt inculcate) cannot be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from <hi>Any</hi> by a <hi>Law</hi> for the <hi>Adminiſtration,</hi> 'Tis true again, perhaps, that ſomething in this Objection, as in the former, may be expreſſed, as to make ſome Men believe, that the Contrivers of this Oath had yet a farther Meaning, and might intend to bind us ſo by it, as to retrench this Liberty; but we are to break thoſe Bonds, and caſt away their Cords, by remembring only, <hi>Theſe</hi> are not the <hi>Lawgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> The greater Number is the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and they are to be believed always to have a fair and equal Meaning in their Acts, and never diſagreeable to the Fundamental Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. We will add,</p>
            <p>As for the very <hi>Contrivers</hi> of theſe <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> thoſe few malicious Men that deſigned by them to exclude ſuch as are now <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> they muſt be thought yet to intend the Admiſſion of the <hi>Loyal Party,</hi> and the Judicious and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious among them that ſuffered for the <hi>King</hi> more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. But if the Meaning of theſe Injunctions be otherwiſe (in the <hi>main purpoſe</hi>) than we interpret them; Thoſe Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Conciencious Men of the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> themſelves, could not ſubmit to them. It will follow, by the leave even of the <hi>Contrivers</hi> of theſe <hi>Acts,</hi> that the meaning which we offer (whatſoever they might harbour in their <hi>By-purpoſe</hi>) muſt be indeed the <hi>Meaning</hi> of the <hi>Lawgiver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To comfirm this, which hath been ſaid above (we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs) as well as here, we will ſuggeſt ſomething for new Strength to it. In an Act of the <hi>Thirteenth</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> there are two things may be inquired. One is, Whether Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Caſe of <hi>Greviance</hi> (for ſo much, at leaſt as theſe things we ſpeak of) by any, not exceeding the number of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64177:16"/>
               <hi>Ten,</hi> is not allowed the Subject? Turn to the Statute-Book, and examine it; and if it be, then could not <hi>All Endeavour,</hi> but ſuch only, which is not <hi>permitted,</hi> be intended in this Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juration, by that <hi>One,</hi> and the <hi>Same Parliament</hi> that paſſed both <hi>Acts.</hi> The other is, Whether after it is there, <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. made a <hi>Premunuire</hi> to ſay, That there lies an Obligation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any from the Covenant, to Endeavour the <hi>Alteration of Government in Church or State,</hi> there be not yet an expreſs Exception, as to all <hi>Parliament Speeches,</hi> and <hi>Endeavours to repeal Statutes,</hi> or <hi>redreſs Grievances?</hi> And if there be, then cannot any one uſe his Reaſon, but he muſ believe our chooſing <hi>Parliament</hi>-Men, this <hi>Petitioning</hi> them, and doing the like things which lie in our Sphere to do, in Order only thereunto, are alſo included. It follows ſtill, that it is an <hi>Endeavour</hi> conſequently in ſome other way, and not this, (which is Parliamentary, and granted) muſt be that which the <hi>Parliament</hi> intended we ſhould abjute, when they put us upon ſuch Impoſitions.</p>
            <p>To enlarge here a little. In that <hi>Decimo Tertio, Car.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. After it is enacted, That no Perſons ſhall procure Hands above the number of <hi>Twenty,</hi> to any Petition for <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Matters Eſtabliſhed by Law in Church or State:</hi> we have a <hi>Provided always, That this Act ſhall not be conſtrued to extend to debar, or hinder any Perſon or Perſons, not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the number of Ten, to preſent any Publick Grievance to any Member, or Members of Parliament.</hi> There are Two Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons now will here go to the Quick. One is, Whether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe <hi>Matters Eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> there be any Excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be underſtood, and what are thoſe Exceptions? And we muſt diſtinguiſh (we think) thus only. <hi>Matters Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by Law,</hi> are ſuch as belong to the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the Government, or the <hi>Adminiſtration.</hi> Thoſe <hi>Matters,</hi> or <hi>Laws,</hi> which belong to the <hi>Original Conſtitution,</hi> (that is according to what the People, at firſt (we muſt ſuppoſe) agreed, when they conſented to a Government) are not indeed within the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64177:17"/>Cognizance of a <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>Alter</hi> them; and for that reaſon, ſuch <hi>Matters</hi> muſt be excepted: But as for any <hi>Matters Eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> that belong only to the <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,</hi> there is no Exception to be apprehended, when the Words are ſo general without any Limitation. If any other Law or Statute be pleaded for putting in ſuch Exception, it muſt be anſwer'd by the Diſtinction offer'd. There <hi>are</hi> no <hi>Matters</hi> (we muſt ſay) excepted by any other Statute, or rather <hi>can</hi> (with reaſon) be excepted, unleſs they belong on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and not the <hi>Adminiſtration.</hi> The O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Queſtion is, Whether the taking away any of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Arch-Deacons</hi> Courts, their <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Canons,</hi> and the like, is ſuch an <hi>Alteration</hi> as belongs to the Adminiſtration of the Government in <hi>England;</hi> that is, Whether it comes within the Cognizance of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> or is in their Power to do it? We know, that ſuch a thing as the Changing of our Monarchy into another ſort of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, were not to be propoſed to <hi>Parliament,</hi> being out of their Cognizance, if the <hi>King</hi> and the <hi>Houſes</hi> were willing to have it: But do the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and their <hi>Courts</hi> ſtand upon the ſame Foundation? 'Tis true, that <hi>Magna Charta</hi> may be pleaded; but <hi>Magna Charta</hi> it ſelf is but a Law for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration. It is, beyond all doubt, in the Power of the <hi>King,</hi> and His <hi>Houſes,</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi>) to regulate the whole External Polity of the Church, and ſo take away <hi>Dioceſan Epiſcopacy</hi> it ſelf, if they pleaſed: And can any one indeed queſtion, whether the taking away ſome <hi>Power</hi> from their <hi>Courts,</hi> or ſome <hi>Officer</hi> belonging to them, or the like, (which yet were to <hi>Alter</hi> the preſent <hi>Government</hi> fo the Church) is not within their Cognizance, or that this <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is not contained in thoſe <hi>Matters Eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> that in general may be <hi>Altered;</hi> and, in caſe of Grievance, be <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned</hi> for, to be <hi>Altered?</hi> And if this be ſtill permitted, the People, according to the Statutes made in the Reign of this King, then could it not be the Intent or Meaning of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64177:17"/>this <hi>Parliament,</hi> that All <hi>Endeavour</hi> to <hi>Alttr</hi> the <hi>Government,</hi> when any thing is grievous in the Church, ſhould be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful;</hi> and when we are brought to diſtinguiſh of ſuch an <hi>Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Alteration,</hi> which is <hi>Warrantable</hi> by Law, and that which is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwarrantable,</hi> then are we come to the right Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the <hi>Lawgiver's</hi> Meaning, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour</hi> which they require us to abjure in the <hi>Oath,</hi> is the One, and not the Other. This is what we ſay all along, and ſtand upon it. <hi>Reader,</hi> lay thy Hand upon thy Heart, and as thou believeſt this <hi>Interpretation,</hi> or believeſt it not, either <hi>Take</hi> or <hi>Forbear</hi> the <hi>Oath,</hi> in the Name of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what think we (after ſome pauſe upon this) of thoſe <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who are <hi>Conformiſts?</hi> Are there not many of them (which is before hinted) Men of Reaſon and Conſcience, judicious, and that fear <hi>God?</hi> And in what ſenſe (judge we) have the <hi>One</hi> ſubſcribed, according to the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> the ſame words which the <hi>Other</hi> ſwears according to the <hi>Act for Corporations?</hi> It is ſtrange, the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt</hi> ſhould make ſuch a ſtand at that Senſe of the Oath and Subſcription propoſed in this Paper, as ſingular and doubtful, which the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> receives as the undoubted and common Senſe of the Kingdom, with all the Judges and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers of the Realm. If they received not this Senſe, they would refuſe them no leſs than we; and if we received it as freely as they, we ſhould ſubmit to them as they do. In like manner, for renouncing the Covenant, What is it alſo they intend by it? Is it nor this, that the Covenant was an unlawful Oath, and therefore binds no body? But let us ask again, do they think that the Covenanting to maintain the <hi>King</hi> (which indeed helpt to bring him in again) and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion, and to Reform our Lives, or the like things, is unlawful; and that therefore no Man is bound thereunto? Certainly, they cannot think ſo; but the Covenanting, to Change the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or <hi>extirpate Prelacy,</hi> and that <hi>without,</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> the Will of the <hi>King,</hi> (which is conſequently in a way Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parliamentary)
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64177:18"/>this is it they judge unlawful, and that ſuch an Oath can oblige no body. And is there any <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> that underſtands himſelf, who does herein diſagree with them? In the name of <hi>God</hi> then, let us come to a right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding on both ſides, of the <hi>Oath,</hi> and of the <hi>Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Let the meaning of the <hi>Oath</hi> be no more than this, <hi>that it is unlawful to take Armes againſt the King, or his Authority,</hi> any where exerted according to Law; and that we will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go about to make any <hi>Change, either in Church or State Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,</hi> but by <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament.</hi> And let the meaning of the <hi>Declaration</hi> alſo, be no more than this (as in the <hi>Firſt Sheet,</hi>) That, <hi>there lies no Obligation upon any from the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to do as they Swear it; It was unlawful in its ſelf to do ſo; and the impoſition of it was illegal.</hi> And when we come to an Agreement <hi>in the ſenſe,</hi> what ſhould hinder us, but we may come alſo to agree <hi>in practiſe,</hi> and do, as one another?</p>
            <p>If any Man indeed remains yet unſatisfied in his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to do as the <hi>Conformiſt</hi> does, (it may be only becauſe he does it) we charge him, notwithſtanding all this which we have ſaid, to forbear: But if indeed he be ſatisfied as to the Senſe, and pretends diſſatisfaction in his Conſcience, and fear of looſing his Soul for the ſaving onely of his Purſe, we muſt in this Caſe (or in this Cauſe rather, at this ſeaſon) lay upon him this Charge alſo, that in refuſing his Compliance with the Law, he muſt give an account to <hi>God</hi> for the refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Duty with it, both to him, and to his Country.</p>
            <p>For our ſelves, if our Arguments ſatisfy any Man, and ſo he complies, we edify that Man, and not ſcandalize him: If they do not, and he forbears, we do him no hurt. It is a Mans own Conſcience, is the Diſcerner to him of his Duty, and he is not to regard another Mans any further than to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void active Scandal; which upon ſuch a warning, that no man follow his Example, unleſs he be ſatisfied with his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, he does prevent as much as he can, in this buſineſs.</p>
            <p>We have done after one Acknowledgment, That the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:64177:18"/>of theſe Sheets are borrowed very much from a Book (that one of us does think, he may make bold with), whoſe deſign is greatly to offer ſuch a kind of <hi>Reſolution</hi> to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> touching our <hi>preſent Impoſitions,</hi> that both they that <hi>Conform to them,</hi> and they that <hi>cannot,</hi> may ſee reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a fair Opinion of one another, and to hope that neither of them do wilfully depart from is, in what they do. The Book was written many years, but Printed onely about three ſince, and is quoted in the Margine of the <hi>Firſt Sheet.</hi> We have reaſon to tell this, both becauſe that which is here of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd may not appear to be written (as ſome may think) on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſerve an Occaſion, having been really the fruit of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years digeſted Thoughts; and alſo becauſe we may not be aſhamed, if we ſhould confeſs, that we had uſed that Book, and made this Collection to ſerve ſo honeſt an End. For, if our Conſcientious and Subſtantial Citizens be put off Publick Offices, and the Miniſters be diſcharged their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, upon the account of theſe Impoſitions: Either the Snare muſt be broken by a general Reception of ſuch a plain, clear, open Interpretation of them as is here preſented to all Men, or they will hold us to theſe Grindſtones, and we ſhall, both in regard to Soul and Body, to Religion and Property, firſt or laſt, be all undone. <hi>Now, when</hi> Mattathias, <hi>and his Friends underſtood hereof, they mourned for them right ſore: And one of them ſaid to another, If we all do as our Brethren have done, they will quickly root us out of the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:64177:19"/>
            <head>THE POST-SCRIPT.</head>
            <p>HAving Printed the <hi>Firſt</hi> of Theſe Papers, or Sheets, Two years, and now Reprinted it the Third year, with Amendment of ſome things, in the leaving out what I judged <hi>inſufficient,</hi> and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying what I have thought needful to confirm that which is <hi>ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent:</hi> I have added two new Sheets, or Papers, to the ſame, in regard to the urgency of the preſent Seaſon, with the ſame Heart, and to the ſame Purpoſe, as at the beginning. We all know, by our own Experience, how ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary it is for the ſame Nations to be preſented in a various Application, according to the Doubts and Objections which are raiſed in Mens Minds, for the giving Satisfaction to thoſe, whoſe Conſciences are really tender, and who diſſent from others, meerly out of the fear of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and not out of <hi>HUmour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think, I have choſe the Charitable Side; and that to write thus as I do, at this Seaſon, is not onely one of the acts of Spiritual Almes, or Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, but a peculiar ſerving my Generation. I cannot tell why, but I find my Spirit is cheeriſhed toward <hi>God,</hi> in this little Service, more than it uſes. If it were onely preſent heat, upon a new thing, I ſhould not take this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it: But when this Subject is (as it were) cool, and no more affecting, than the inward Teſtimony it brings with it, as to my hopes, it will do good, I cannot tell but ſuch Impreſſions may abode ſomething. I wiſh, it be not this, that theſe Impoſitions will be continued, and preſſed upon us yet with more Regiour; ſo that many good Men ſhall have Occaſion for this <hi>Paper,</hi> that after no Man perhaps, may be found that dares to attempt the like.</p>
            <p>I know, that as the <hi>Errata</hi> of a Book can have no Amendment, when the <hi>Book</hi> it ſelf can; ſo cannot I my ſelf ſee my own weakneſſes, or Failings,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64177:19"/>when the <hi>Reader</hi> of theſe Sheets (that ſees more than I) may diſcover them. But ſo far as I can judge, according to the Tenuity of my underſtanding, there is more ſaid in theſe few Sheets to the very Purpoſe, to which they are writ, than hath been ſaid by others, or any where, unleſs by the ſame Paper; and I hope, that which is ſaid, is full and ſatisfactory. The proud Man, that would be praiſed in what he does, does ordinarily diſpraiſe himſelf, that others may commend him: But I ſpeak of my own Paper, as I would of Anothers. It is a great many thoughts I am ſure, even the thoughts of many years is digeſted into theſe few Sheets; and I do not offer my <hi>Brethren,</hi> that which cost me nothing.</p>
            <p>As for my writing under a <hi>Plural</hi> Name, the <hi>Reader</hi> muſt know, that though it be <hi>One</hi> is the Compiler, or Author of theſe Sheets altogether; it is more than <hi>One</hi> conſented, and conſent to the Publication. The firſt Sheet, after it was done at firſt, was ſhew to a Great Perſon particularly, whoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding and Faithfulneſs, the Cry generally can truſt in ſuch Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, (for it was thought good by one of the Sheriffs choſe for that year, I ſhould do ſo) and he adviſed that the Paper ſhould come out thus, and not in the Name of a Single Perſon. He had it a Day or two to Read, and changed nothing otherwiſe, but gave this judgment of it frankly, It was well done: My <hi>Brethren,</hi> to whom I ſhewed it beſides, were not like to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict what he adviſed, but thought it very prudent, and it came out ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <p>I muſt give notice now, that <hi>P. 9. l. 20.</hi> the word <hi>[it]</hi> which is fallen out at the Preſs, muſt be carefully preſerved, leſt you miſtake the Senſe.</p>
            <p>Note alſo, That in the Marginal <hi>Note,</hi> p. <hi>5,</hi> there to the Nominative Caſe wanting to the Verb <hi>Condemn.</hi> Read therefore, <hi>and the impoſers of this Oath condemn,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Note, moreover, that there needs ſome farther Explication in the place: For ſuppoſe a Man to be ſatisfied in all other Scruples but this One, that he apprehends in the late Times, the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Cauſe was the right, and not the <hi>King's,</hi> and he cannot therefore take the Oath, becauſe he thinks he ſhall thereby Condemn that Cauſe. The plain Anſwer to this Man is, that though he cannot but believe, that the Major Part of the Houſes that paſſed this Oath, were of a contrary judgment to his; yet is he not to think it was their intent, that every one who takes this Oath ſhould meddle with that Matter, and Judge of that Cauſe, ſo as to condemn one ſide, and justify another: but that he ſhould onely judge, think, believe, and declare, that to raiſe another War, or <hi>do now as they did then</hi> (as we ſpeak) is unlawful; and he that does not Judge ſo, or cannot diſcern this, must forbear to take the Oath, out of Question. The <hi>Summa Poteſtas</hi> in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64177:20"/>this Land, lies in the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Two Houſes,</hi> as one Conporation, (we have intimated) and when they were divided, a Man may judge the Constitution Diſſolved, and the People at Liberty; and conſequently, that they might then do that, in that peculiar Caſe, which can never be done out of it, without reſisting <hi>the Ordinance of God;</hi> which to do, we know is Sin. This is the Anſwer to that Scruple, being more darkly there ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.</p>
            <p>There remains only, that I ſupply here the <hi>Fifth Reaſon</hi> (according to the Firſt Paper) for Printing theſe Sheets, that for want of Room was left out in the <hi>Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It pleaſed Providence to call ſome Perſons to the Office who have been the</hi> better <hi>inabled (to ſpeak modeſtly) to Hold the ſame, upon the ſatisfaction which is couched in this Paper; and if it be of great Concern at this time, that ſuch Men do Hold Sheriffs, who are willing to deny their</hi> own <hi>Advantage, (not ſeek it) for the ſake of the</hi> Publick: <hi>It is yet of greater concern that by the publiſhing our grounds for their ſatisfaction, many in diſtreſs about the</hi> Oxford <hi>Act, may be relieve, and a Way opened for many of the like ſubſtantial Citizens, of known Piety, Loyalty, and Ability, to be brought into Corporations, throughout the Nation, to the great ſervice of the King and Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page, 9 line. 20. read. <hi>Sware it,</hi> p. 24. l. 9. for <hi>expreſſed</hi> 1. <hi>ſo preſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64177:20"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
